oh yeah the other thing is it's so
campus is being heard I also apologized
for the but what may be like low quality
video and maybe even like some
choppiness right I'm sitting in my my
parents ranch in rural Texas and the
internet connections that's it's not
urban so what they do I'll have to make
do a lot of that's happening right now
and some videos so we all just have to
make do given the circumstances so as I
mentioned before we started recording I
thought it'd be good if we pick up on
whether the thing we came to in our last
discussion when so a lot of people seem
to be appreciating and in terms of what
I'm reading in the comments was this I
this this idea of faith and the faith
that takes you through a transformative
process and I propose to you I didn't
mean it as a definition but although all
sort of reorder it again the idea of
faith not as a willful assertion of a
proposition mmm-hmm but a cultivated
sense of being in in a participatory
knowing of a transformative process that
continuity of contact rather than trying
to bring some kind of you know
argumentative closure and conclusion and
that seems to me to be extremely
relevant both to the longer arc of the
transformation that we're facing right
now and this shorter and more acute arc
that we're facing right now in our
culture and what I'd like to discuss
with you is what you think about that
and then tie that back to our ongoing
discussion of the religion that's not a
religion and and then that's all I want
to say I'm not I don't want to put too
many constraints but I want to give sort
of a context and then let's see what
emerges in our discussion
yeah well all right so just to I mean
just to begin the beginning obviously my
mind has immediately turned to the
narrative that you told about the
transition in the West and in particular
that that switch that began with the
reading in your head yeah as opposed to
reading any group yeah
and that transition towards
propositional writing towards logic yeah
and towards the notion that it well
stated phrases is the thing yeah and
something about how man it's just such a
beautiful notion of thinking about this
idea of faith as being groundedness
being solidity as being oriented like
integrity like I actually recently
mentioned something about the need for
integrity in it several people commented
in a sense of like confusion about what
integrity means and I guess that's
reasonable it's quite reasonable yeah
it's not obvious what that means um and
to me the pointing was something like
like you know you can think about the
structural integrity of a wall that it's
laid on a solid foundation and then each
brick is securely right on top of the
burqa above it so that it can hold its
weight and it stays out like it's
well-built
there's a integrity so that is well
built and it can you can do things with
this notion of a impractical the word
the word faith having a fundamentally
agentic yeah like turning in the word
meaning like moving it from the semantic
domain into the nernst of means to an
end right into the faith has something
about that which is has a as a
well-founded reliable means to an end
mm-hmm
yeah it's so funny maybe think about it
like if you kind of transposition in
that direction a like a basketball
player a truly masterful basketball
player you've seen certain circumstances
when they shoot the shot and they just
turn around and walk away because they
know well before the ball is hit the
hoop that it's going in yeah that's
faith yeah it's the faith of the master
knowing that their tool will do with the
tool is intended that their will will
carry itself out in the world with
artistry and a certain elegance because
the competence is just there like they
just know that that feels to me like
that's getting in the right direction
how's that landing for you I like parts
of it and I want to I want to sort of
open up other parts of it because the
thing that concerns me and what you said
let me say what concerns me in that let
me say what I liked what landed for me
what concerns me is part of that
historical narrative was also the shift
with Luther right and you get the shift
towards sort of willful assertion that
and that God is also a purely willing
agent willing in the sense not of
wanting but of actively enforcing his
will on the world the imposition
position notion mm-hmm yeah and so and
they and we know some of the dangerous
offshoots of this which is the idea of
faith is sort of you know almost a
magical will imposition of your will on
the world you'll just sort of will the
world to be what you want it to be and
and I don't think you want to put your
finger on that I don't think you want to
say that because I know what we
discussed before yeah so so there's a so
let me be thrown in front of the
metaphor that comes to my mind as you're
talking and they both have to do with
water so one has to do with the notion
of a kayak in the river the other one is
a surfer on a surfboard
yeah yeah and I think there's a really
big distinction between a surfer who
really has this sense that he is going
to out paddled the ocean you know his
will
is the thing right that it's a matter of
almost like a brutal forcing of mastery
on the natural environment the ocean is
a great example because in most cases
this just straight isn't gonna happen to
be a good surfer it's first and foremost
you've learned that lesson that
primarily your responsibility is
sensitivity to be aware of the flows
that you were in meshed in right right
and there's something about your choices
like a trim tab in the in the Bucky
fuller sense there there's a there's an
opening there's a pop there's a place
where your choice makes a difference
mm-hmm that your your will has a place
in the larger context and that and then
then faith is this sense of like being
held in surfing it literally it's called
being in the pocket right yeah yeah
literally be to know how to sense what's
happening around you and to respond to
what's happening in a way that you are
held in the pocket it's a very move away
Sensibility
right right that's what I'm talking
about in that direction okay that's very
much in line with what I was thinking
when I was trying to propose this idea
of this dynamic sense of continuity of
contact with an unfolding process which
of course is exactly what's happening in
this area and then there's you brought
in an extra dimension which you often do
wonderfully with your with your
visualizations I love the way you do
that by the way you will be articulating
something conceptually you'll bring it
into a visual metaphor and then the
visual metaphor unfolds unpacking
something in the phenomenology that
isn't immediately referenced in the
concept because you brought up this idea
of like the pocket and finding the sweet
spot right it's nice to talk to you
again by the way it's been too long yeah
I agree I like it a lot too and so I
like that I'd like iiiii cuz you know
you know being a martial artist Tai Chi
Chuan and stuff like that they're like
it's part of its of course getting into
a flow state but part of its also
getting into like you said getting into
the pocket so I take it that like
there's there there's a there's a
normativity to faith if you'll allow me
like you can do it you can do it better
or worse you can think of the surfer you
know maintaining sort of a continuity of
contact with the wave
but they're sort of clumsy right and
then you the one who gets if you'll
allow me a term I've been working on you
know gets an optimal grip on the
situation right and they find that
reciprocity with the worlds right
there's that deep sort about one minute
and then they have a sense of right and
it's not something you know even with
the power of a skill I would say that
it's a knowing at a much deeper level
you you know that you you you have this
sense of a deep kind of conformity and
at one MIT with things yeah gives you
the sense that you're in you're in that
sweet spot with respect to how something
is unfolding is that part of what you're
putting your finger on yeah absolutely I
really like the fact that you highlight
that notion of that one minute because
it is diplom I first-person experience
when I'm in those circumstances I guess
that sense that sense of sort of going
and dropping away and an extension and a
sensitivity and you know and of course
the classic example is that the moment
that you are aware of it or you're
thinking about it you get in your head
you're not in it anymore right
and that's important right in the
context of this notion of propositional
well that's exactly right so there's two
things I want to talk about there one is
exactly that because I'm really
interested as you know and dialectic and
how it affords deal logos I'm interested
in about this this you know this
interplay between dropping in I'll use
your metaphor it's it's a good one and
then maybe I'll use my metaphor stepping
back and looking at and right and that
there's a kind of higher order place you
can get there - yes that's got its own
sweet spot right absolutely yeah yeah
absolutely completely in fact you're and
again I just had the first-person
experience so there's like a middle spot
it's a bad place the top shot of both
yeah there's this really interesting
thing where you're like actually in both
of those places and they really do
support each other yes yes and that's
the kind of faith in dialectic that you
see in the Platonic dialogues I'm
reading a really good book I can't
remember the name of the author's name
starts with an R real cocky I think I
might be getting it wrong it's a
heidegger's Platonism guy sent it to me
and he's unpacking this whole thing that
could play
thought that ultimately there's a deep
kind of faith in dialectic and Plato
because and confederal argues that when
you're doing this process you altima
can't put it into words which sounds odd
for dialectic right but his whole point
is you you do this so something catches
fire right that is ultimately non
propositional but nevertheless that
doesn't mean you can just do whatever
you want there is a normativity there is
there is this there is this guiding mass
of it yeah yeah yeah yeah again Hague's
absolutely and it's beauty it's
beautiful it's like you could say me
even like a mm-hmm this new ship of
conformity that there's a shape there is
a shape to it there is a shape that's
all there is to it if you know if you
don't grab a ball like this then you
were not going to be successful in
holding the ball like if you hold it
like this it's gonna slide up your hand
was that yeah that's the optimum of
gripping again the dynamic yeah so that
brings me to kind of the other other
point I wanted to we don't have to get
to it immediately but I want to try and
situate that in terms of again the
religion that's not a religion this idea
because I want to add one more dance to
it absolutely very powerful
yeah and I'm seeing it unfold in real
time actually okay great
because the one more thing I would want
to add to that which i think is implicit
especially if the surfer right is
getting an optimal grip on a continually
shifting situation is the surfer is also
going through some kind of
transformative process now in the
surfing situations it's transformation
of there's their skillset and their
sensitivity but what we're talking about
I think when we're talking about the
religion that's not a religion is a much
more profound and comprehensive
transformation and so what I mean is for
discussion is taking this notion we're
starting to craft of faith but then
saying but what does that look like when
it's a faith that's gonna take you
through this much more comprehensive and
profound transformation does that does
that make sense as a question yeah
absolutely let me just try throw
something out that occurs to me and I
apologize that this is a
a bit too topical but yeah I'm gonna use
the coronaviruses or the that's the
unfolding meta-crisis as I'm referring
to it because you have to think about a
lot of stuff besides just a virus yeah
in this context of faith in this context
of religion yeah
and it's really quite fascinating
actually it's almost like a mirror
reflection of the Black Plague yes you
and I talked about this like last time
yeah yeah so here's here's what's going
to happen at least in some places in
some context is that some people will
take faith in this sense that we're
talking about mmm it's just to say that
they will find a way to come into a how
do you say it a dynamic conformity yeah
yeah with what is really unfolding yeah
which we should say that they will make
good choices they will they will make
choices that are right in relationship
to the reality that they find themselves
in and to who they are or at the place
that they are at in relationship to
themselves to their own bodies to to the
people who they are with the
relationships that they are near and and
in fact in extending it and if you fight
over this is happening in real time for
example many many communities around the
world we're the beginning to realize
that a lot of the help that they need
we'll only in candling be found among
the people who they are nearby right and
to the degree to which you and what I'm
saying is that that's actually a
discovery of what is in fact actually
real mm-hmm
that's a reality it is simply the
reality that in a context like this to
be able to rely on your neighbors is a
very a good strategy it's a good place
to be and to be able to be relied on by
your neighbors is a good place to be yes
trust and by the way of non-trivial yeah
all these things exactly good faith
competence integrity trustworthiness all
these sort of things that are old-school
virtues for good reasons as our friend
Jordan Peterson sort of famously tried
to hammer into the consciousness that is
a coming to faith thread that building
of an actual capacity to do so
all right now it's not the hope that it
exists but the learning the relearning
and the many ways does the rediscovery
of what it means to be able to have
integrity and what it means to be able
to have trustworthiness and and how to
do
so across a larger group of people had
to be to be a neighbor to be neighborly
and to be a good neighbor in the context
of crisis is an embodiment of this face
that we're talking about right in in a
larger fashion I'm on a larger body and
the the beautiful thing about the
environment they're in right now is that
it has this beautiful that the the
constants between salience and relevance
we are making we are forced to make
choices yeah we find out very quickly
whether the basis of choice was a good
basis of choice right right it has
meaning it lands right there are
consequences yes so this is a very this
is sort of an optimal learning
environment for for building faith I'm
really enjoying this but I really like
the idea of being able to recover this
this notion so well so deeply from the
false narrative that has presented it as
being kind of maximally maladaptive so
there's a bunch of things we could riff
on that so let's put a pin in because
I've learned so we can try and get I
wanna I want to get to this the
connection to integrity and I would want
to talk about integrity in terms of the
process of integration mm-hmm-hmm what
that looks like because integrity I
think has degenerated in our common
conception into a kind of steadfastness
which i think is a component but nowhere
is sufficient for what you're trying to
put your finger on the other thing we
might do is pick up on what you've just
said which i think is really important
is which is the contrast class which is
more traditional notions of faith ah
right so I mean what immediately comes
to mind are two notions that we've
already discussed but maybe I think we
should maybe excavated a bit more that
we want to say no this isn't what we
need right now what this isn't what
we're talking about at least one is
where as I said before willful
imposition that you're going to force
things which is the opposite of whoa way
right I'm going to want things it's
right instead of fall it's you know the
the Chinese metaphors finding the grain
of the wood and knowing how to follow
the grain of the wood but nevertheless
you can still carve the wood
but you follow the grain of the wood
rather than forcing against the grain
and and really risking tearing the whole
thing apart and hurting yourself
so and there's that and and I think
these two are shadows of each other in
the almost in the Union sense I think
they're the they're both sides of Luther
yeah not not to make him the villain
here and then the other one is and
something that you put your finger on
which is something I think we need to do
which is a kind of magical Hope which is
oh well we just have to have faith which
is the sense of you know something
completely miraculous and external to me
is going to you know save me and save
the situation and that that to me seems
Oh also equally dangerous
in dangerous times like these so the
idea that we're gonna force the grain
and you can you can see that right with
you know there's been political
responses where people just sort try to
deny the reality or will it away by
assertion no no it's real where
everything's fine the economy's gonna be
great get all that sort of stopped and
then there's the other well we just
tough that faith where it means we just
sort of have to hope and I'm actually
I'm very critical of the notion and it's
a classical notion he goes back to st.
Paul I'm very I'm usually very
respectful of st. Paul but his notion of
defining faith in terms of hope
I think is problematic because I find
hope a very problematic thing because
it's different because it's we do the
same thing we can rescue hope yes i I
hear what you're saying right so yeah
I'm quite happy to rescue hope I was
gonna say that I wasn't rejecting hope I
find hope ambiguous and equivocal in a
way that's very dangerous right right
and so that we could we could try and
work that out and that that's my
critique of Paul's notion that faith is
hope for things that we don't have
evidence for or something like that that
we haven't seen and what I what I'm
trying to get at is you know what I see
wrong with them it parallels the
criticism I made sorry I'm going on but
there's
there's an argument here it parallels
the criticisms I made sort of you know
Locke and Rousseau where you know Locke
is a purely passive epistemology and
that's the magical hope version of faith
I just possibly wait for the miracle
waiting for a miracle right and then
there and then or you have Rousseau's
which is the willful imposition I'm
gonna make the miracle happen
right I'm gonna write I'm gonna and it
seems to me that for reasons analogous
to why both of those epistemologies are
seriously questionable I think both of
those notions of faith as magical will
and magical hope should equally be
rejected so that was an argument
I wanted something absolutely I think I
said and I mean as far as I'm concerned
that seems obvious like yes yes yes and
I think your framing is just right like
one has this energy imposition yeah and
I think the way I categorize they both
are characteristics of the maladaptive
the relationship to reality yes I agree
that's why I made the analogy to the
epistemology because I think yes
apologies are ultimately now adaptive
ways of understanding the acquisition of
knowledge and and then the way of doing
the the transmogrification of that
simply to choose I'm Calvin and Hobbes
soon as the what is right relationship
to reality and it's kind of a very
simple question yeah what is what is it
what is it intimate subtle honorable
humble like there's how does one come
into right relationship with reality few
think about like in the context of this
notion of the meaning crisis mm-hmm you
can I want to put a fine point and it
may be like what it's at the center of
the meaning crisis is the lack of the
right relationship to reality I think
that is extremely well said and very
astute I like that in fact I would I
would accept that as a summation of the
central project of the whole series Wow
all right that's good news then we're
we're we're doing the thing we should be
doing yeah
Wow so that's interesting because I have
heard in religious contexts faith
sometimes described as being in a right
relationship or knowing how knowing when
there's a finesse element in here of
being
knowing how and when to be in a right
relationship with God so I have heard
that that's not Raman it in my religious
past but I do remember that being posed
as a a way of understanding yeah I mean
I think this all comes down to the thing
we talked about last time which is this
sort of terrible trap that we get into
where we try to force ourselves into
being effective by training doctrine
rather than training capacity yes yes
say okay somebody wise once discovered
that if you follow these three rules the
likelihood that you'll be in right
relationship to God would be in right
relationship to reality is very high
yeah well it turns out that it's one of
the easier to get somebody to read three
rules and just kind of repeat it over
and over again than it is to cultivate
in them the native capacity to actually
make effective choices in themselves yes
and so we kind of lose track of the
thing we start to try to go in that
direction let's say yeah I mean some
sense it's a developmental laziness this
seems to be a consistent trap that we
fall into yeah I noticed that when I'm
reading Gonzales book dialogue and
dialectic and he talks about the two
traps that Plato has Socrates constantly
this skill and Charybdis that he's
constantly trying to steer the
conversation between one is the obvious
nosov common sense mm-hmm
and then the other is what you're saying
the satisfaction with technical
definition kind of empty theorizing a
theorizing that has no existential
challenge or import attached yeah yeah
yeah beautiful and then you can see how
thank you that's a good selling credit
so you have a it's very similar to her
it's not exactly the same but very
similar just they add the bifurcation
and did it it's like have a lazy
disengaged and sometimes even like a
truculent or diffident relationship to
reality which is the common sense yeah
No and then there's a that there's a
distancing and a actually it's
interesting yeah that doctrine said is
very much the mastery domain we
basically say you know fuck reality our
rules are the rules and we're gonna
impose the rigor of the rule we're gonna
discipline ourselves so vigorously and
our discipline is actually going to
force reality to conform to us yeah I
think and I mean that's that's the
that's the attraction of ideology right
is I can hammer everything I can I could
hammer this doctrine on to the world
right yeah so but the but and so what
what I'm okay so we we might have a four
dimensional thing or what might have a
two dimensional thing I don't know quite
what we're mapping that the mapping is
yeah because we have an active we have
an activity passivity golden mean we're
trying to get between and then there's
also a golden mean I don't know know
what I'm doing with the vertical it
doesn't mean anything it's just an
alternative dimension but there is a
golden mean between two kinds of obvious
misses I'd like to say there's like you
said there's the the imposition of the
doctrine but but I think that common
sense also carries with it a kind of
imposition which is right which is an
intuitive kind of imposition my into my
unquestioned untutored in here's what
I'm trying to say we often mistake the
rapidity and obviousness of intuition
with a deep with the kind of competence
that you and I are talking about here
and now absolutely right we often we
offer isn't their actual work isn't it
like the dunning-kruger effect or
something like that it is a very
specific realization that that is the
case yes so what and again I get the
feeling that the flavor for that of me
as that sort of like a truculence
a and a laziness yeah there's definitely
a laziness that isn't present in the
ideologue there's a laziness in that and
you know and the obvious 'no sand of
common sense yeah it's really
interesting so think about that so this
just do common sense and then notice
this again came embody in a visual
metaphor please and you've got the the
shaker the shaker the shaker chair which
sorry
the shakers like the the famous yes yes
yes yes yes so that is a this sort of
beautiful elegant instantiation of the
golden mean meaning that there is a
simplicity to it but also a skillfulness
to it and artfulness to it mm-hmm
it is a hand that is deftly played it
does not go too much in the direction of
frills all right but nor is it clumsy
right right so on the right hand side of
that in our in our structure we can put
kind of the the Khaimah like a
ramshackle hammered together skill this
shamble you know an upside down box you
know falling apart right right right
right common sense in the rough lazy
diffident sensitivity right right and
then of course on the left hand side we
can put like a louis xiv rokoko chair
where the the the artifice and the the
preciousness of our human built you know
virtue signaling replacing virtue
situation right that's it because those
are a desert are big tensions it's funny
you can actually see that a little bit
in our political domain the vice of of
team red is kind of the gross coarse
lazy truculent common sense yeah yeah
and the vice of team blue is virtually
signaling out competing virtue yeah
ideology or preference over reality nice
I think both are full of ice I'm just
saying that you want to find their vice
I agree with that yeah I think that
that's well said that there is that
there is that malformed it nests on both
ends in the way you're talking about
so that then I think is now I feels to
me like we're steering back then to the
normativity issue and we're talking
about a golden mean and we're talking
about a virtue and that seems to me to
be working in marketing us back to the
need to discuss the integrity and the
integration hmm yeah okay so may I may I
do something we haven't done yet me
actually read something please from the
from my friend
yes Akiko camera I quoted him recently
and on exactly this question of
integrity hmm
so the as you might imagine from his
name he's Japanese the Japanese word
toku tete in Chinese which is usually
translated as virtue also means power or
integrity mm-hmm toku is the
consciousness of the whole that makes
her life coherent consistent and
integral therefore toku is integrity
antoku is also power because through
toku your vision action and results
become coherent and consistent and then
he talks about the notion of integrity
the integration the coming together I
lost it
too bad I'm full unfortunately the quote
that I quoted did not include the piece
that I was looking for it's still a good
quote to begin with them yeah so let's
go back to just first principles and
what we're talking about this notion of
integration yes and and then hole right
a hole it's an integration oh yes
there's some really good stuff there
well part of it part of it is so what
comes to my mind immediately is again
because I'm working on it so much but I
guess also because I'm committed to it
existentially is plato's deep I think
it's one of his profound insights about
the deep belonging together of inter
intra psychic integration and right
ontological integration with the world
that one man there's a there's a there's
three dimensions of that one myth you
have to be at one with yourself and that
we have to get beyond a trivial meaning
of that and so hopefully we can unpack
that at the FBI one with reality and
then those two at one myths are all
right one with each other they're
mutually affording each other that awful
way and I think for me the normativity
then of faith is the normativity of what
is affording me a progression towards an
optimal grip that brings about inner
peace and an optimal grip that gives me
ontological depth perception and then in
right and then an optimal grip that
makes the two of them right reciprocally
open so the world and me are
reciprocally opening each other rather
than reciprocally narrowing this is
let's play guitar yeah so I have a I had
a sense of some kind of sound that I
would like to make okay but to
successfully achieve that there has to
be an integration in the interior there
has to be a smoothness of the flow from
the rising sensibility that is actually
effortlessly and seamlessly executed
through the body to a conformant
conformity of my hand to its shape which
is now my my interior is expressing
itself as an exterior which is
manifested directly as an actual
conformity of the shape of my hand right
through the objective shape of the
guitar right at which point I now strum
right but now the objective space the
note is sounded the sound that I was
sensing in myself is now sounded in the
outside and I can hear it and it lands
in me which then moves me from a note to
the next note right and your reciprocal
feedback right now you're actually
moving into music yep we're now making
music and that if it is certain point if
you have not for example skillfully
trained yourself and you know you get a
cramp in your hand this is a lack of
integrity in the interior like the way
that your muscles are that you're out of
integrity when playing you're pushing
yourself too hard
they're cramping your hand will make
your ability to be in conformity with
the outside world
you will miss the note right right right
right and for an equal equally if
there's something
about the nature of your relationship
with the outside world at the note you
play as sour your finger hits the string
a little bit off then the world the
sourness of the note will break the
connection the year within your interior
and you will lose or may lose the the
space that allows you to be able to
flowing it through you that's a for me a
concrete example of what you're talking
about I hope it was not too too banal
but I like like making no no not at all
I think I think what's really again to
unpack the phenomenology that comes in
your imaginal presentation I like the
way music is not only doing you know the
harmonization between the inner and
outer alignment music is also as you
mentioned earlier right and this is I
think also part of what we meant by
integrity music is really getting your
salience landscaping and your reality
contact to be really tightly bound
together I mean that's that's one of the
reasons why we love music so much is it
represents to us sort of an ideal state
in which our salience tracking and our
pattern detection are like smoothly
smoothly in sync together I think that's
part of if you'll allow me part of the
beauty of music and Plato talks a lot
about especially in the symposium right
you know that that there's that the this
dialogical faith brings with it a sense
of beauty a sense of beauty which isn't
the same thing as a sense of
pleasantness right Rilke is very good
for teaching us if beauty doesn't mean
the same thing as pleasantness or
entertaining beauty and put us on the
border of awe or even horror as well
yeah it's because you beauty and scary
does a beautiful book of what it's this
beautiful gem of a book on on the
experience of beauty and how it and this
is her language it shouldn't be equated
with truth and goodness but it trains us
hmm and goodness and so beauty is a
sense that you're getting this kind of
flowing at one mint and you're you're
you're coupling salience and right and
truth tracking together
you're getting you know a transformation
of your deeper competence and beauty is
a way of saying ah to all of that yeah
beautiful yeah there's a sense as you're
saying it out of like this just a very
slow I think is Martha Graham just like
a single perfectly smooth motion of the
hand right right and in that sense like
the would you call the competence or the
the the the interior exterior the
balancing length is exactly says it's an
implicitly no no integrally unavoidably
a relationality between the interior and
the exterior and a way of actually using
that the factor that relationality to
achieve a smoothness yes um subtlety and
smoothness to it which doesn't mean
smoothness doesn't mean a reductive
homogeneity this I mean you can have a
lot of fine grained movement and
differentiation but the thing about
integrity right is its heat right I mean
I mean that that's why I often prefer
the notion of complexification because
when a system is capable of
differentiating and then maintaining
integration throughout that
differentiation I think that's when
we're talking about it getting the
ability to ride the wave of uncertainty
to surf the wave of uncertainty to go
back to one of your earlier metaphors
and add to allude to a book by Andy
Clark as well I guess well and I was
also brought to mind the works of
Christopher Alexander mmm the the
architect who one of his great polymaths
who his discipline was architecture but
he ended up using architecture as a
primary medium to then explore all
things right and what's nice about is
that you can actually very clearly get a
sense of this sort of golden mean that
the homogeneity is not beautiful and
what you can't sort of a mess is not
beautiful yeah there's a particular
location where you actually really need
to have the right mixture of symmetries
and bowel
said actually asymmetries and you know
characteristics of what that a beautiful
physical environment you know houses and
buildings a nation at you know parks
look like which is nice i mean it's its
interest you can discover that that when
you find someone who's thought deeply
about this and it spend time out in a
particular discipline and particularly
they've done it multimodal they haven't
done it in a discipline that actually
begin to become transparent matic that
they generally end up coming to more or
less the same place this is um that's a
great observation
so i mean to me now it almost becomes
how's it work it's simple but not easy i
think it's a right way of putting it mhm
we have more or less two questions i
guess these are the two questions that
people who is struggling with forever
but but the challenge is to get good at
it not to try to have to have done with
it right you know one question is just
to be aware of what are the the
practices the heuristics not the rules
but the rules of thumb loosely held
guidances that allow us to develop in
this way how do we did the there's a
couple of pi day oh and the greek i
think um yeah and then the other one is
two traps like what are the what are the
things that cause us to go astray how do
how do we find ourselves off the path
and just becoming you aware of and wise
and able to respond to that as it's
occurring that's the religion that's not
a religion i just the combination of
those two things I think that's rectus
built in life in yourself and in others
that would pick up on the contrast
between schleiermacher and Schley and
Schlegel's take on Plato you know Shlomo
was the person who did that the
translations of the dialogue that sort
of started the modern school scholarship
around Plato and it sort of fragmented
into two schools one school or you could
again I wish I could remember the author
of this book same but the dogmatist
there say here's Plato's arguments and
here's his theories he's got the theory
of the forum there's
arguments you know that's how I was
taught Plato and then you get people who
are called the holistic happy with
either one of these titles but that's
the title that's being used and they say
no you can't look at just the arguments
alright and you and I've talked about
this it's it's the drama it's the
characters it's the relationship between
the dialogues if they look at this whole
sort of thing and how they all fit
together to get what Plato is pointing
out and each side has its strengths and
weaknesses and their mockery seems a his
work is ambiguous there's a tension in
his work and that's why it gave birth to
these two competing schools but he was
actually at one point quite close
friends with Schlegel and Schlegel
actually proposes no no what you need is
the two together
Plato's Plato wrote and dialogues
because dialogue is the only form that
will actually write represent in a very
loose sense of that word represent the
wisdom that Plato is trying to get it's
not just a pedagogical tool it's not
just it's not just an ornamentation it's
not just right that the way that what
Plato is pointing to can only be
captured biologically in clear marker
put this that in terms of the religion
of the future which was that he
explicitly put it this way that the
religion of the future will find a way
to reintegrate the philosopher and the
poet which is what I keep seeing you
doing and I mean that as a compliment my
friend I see I keep seeing you trying to
bring you know the philosophical
argumentation and articulation into a
smooth to use your very pertinent
adjective into a smooth integration with
poesis with image making and the
phenomenological exploration and what's
important about all of this is you know
slagle said that this is the way you
have to set yourself not just mentally
but existentially in order to be in
conformity and he literally used this
word with the inexhaustible Ness of
reality hmm
like that hi guys
[Laughter]
another one
Oh going down for a nap okay Don have a
nice nap we'll see you in a few hours
hey can we say how did a real quick sure
do you want me to pause it no it's fine
Camila one come on up go quick come here
hey kiddo yeah she's been quite enjoying
the extended experience at grandparents
house of course is there anything more
wonderful than grandparents well I
imagine grandparents would say
grandchildren but happy wonderful that
market he can stay the dogs in here as
well now so reboot back um yeah I was
trying to point out how the the form of
the dialogue Slagel thought it was
indispensable because it is the place in
which you will get that smooth flowing
integration between ah my right and
Police's yeah and so it we came up from
is you're saying that was this notion of
the opening the holding open of that
space yes the guy logos the the ability
to actually recognize that there's
actually something there there's a space
of the dialogue that your action in
relationship and so when you're reading
Plato's dialogues Department if you if
you collapse that into a text then
you're not in dialogue with the dialogue
that's right if you can maintain the
dialogue oh so you can now be in
dialogue with the dialogue and that
space opens up right and that and that's
that you know it's in this case with us
it's a little bit more obvious because
it's easy to imagine that there are
changes going on in you and there are
changes going on in me it's a little
harder to imagine there are changes
going on in Plato's dialogue when I'm in
a relationship with it but right
nonetheless it is the case that it has
it has the depth to lurk there was
superb opening I mean people had the
experience that truly rich pieces of
work yeah that's it right that's the
philosopher and the poet yes yes poetry
has that characteristic that if I go
through life if I change through life
and I will integrate life into myself
when I come back to a poem that is
deeply meaningful it also has changed
yes yes yes
yeah I've talked about that as what I
mean by an experience of sacredness that
ongoing continuity of affordance of
reciprocal opening so is is part of what
we're putting our finger on that is that
faith is a cultivated sensitivity to
this kind of richness right yeah that's
really yeah that's very nice so what
happens is it to me is that I'm holding
the previous conversation about faith
right here yes I have like a kind of a
very embodied sense of almost a kind of
practical prosaic element to it like our
surfer yeah right who in a moment's
gonna come and say hey no dude I'm doing
this other thing but then you say what
you just said
and so I suddenly see it from a
different angle and yes very much so yes
actually I'm obviously in some sense
obviously right it's like the the the
tracing or following the track the the
tasting the the sensing in the flow of
experience the the we call this it's
like um the trajectory yeah yeah and
that is this that is the sacred that is
the dispositional relationship with
reality that places us on the path right
that's the sacred the thing that moves
us in that direction yes I agree with
that so I'm really interested then in
back by the way this is what hits me
with hope so I'd like to try to take a
shot at her oh let's take a shot at hope
then let's take a shot sorry that's not
very aggressive I didn't mean it that
way
go ahead
III have a very ambivalent attitude
towards hope part of its my
fundamentalist upbringing and part of it
personal experience both myself and
people that have been close to where
I've seen people trapped in life sucking
potentially life destroying
relationships because of hope right yes
yes so right so there's there's a word
in in Buddhism G you'll know but I can't
quite recall it I think it starts with
the sea and essentially a good
disposition to have mmm like what's this
with a nice solid disposition to be in a
it's not compassion it's definite not
complacency you know it's physically
this is mmm say this is what hope really
ought to be it's physically in a place
of being very very much in relationship
with what is real right but then
choosing to orient towards it in a
nonreactive stance does it also shift
things so that choosing to orient in an
honor like is hope
I like this I'm get I'm getting a visual
image like if you sort of got this right
fluid optimal grip on a complex
situation and it's predominantly this
way but because you actually have you're
really in touch you see a possibility
here and that your stance towards it
might actually afford that possibility
coming forth is it yes like that yes
exactly it and and this is key like
again is it's very it's a adducing it's
a drawing out if you try to if you try
to teleport to the end you're engaging
in the magical thinking that has often
has claimed hope yes yes yes very
different right it's that notion of one
no it's like flow in one day if I if I
get back on my heels if I second-guess
myself if I assume the worst
then I will destabilize my capacity I
would be out of balance I will no longer
be able to be in conformity
and for me with what's actually
happening right right and then there's
something like a again because there's
in back into the surfing metaphor it's
the you know if you imagine the surfer
and the surfer is seeing the spot like
they see the pocket in the wave breaking
you might say they hoped themselves into
the spot right right there's a
combination of exactly two things one is
holding a dispositional attitude of
fluid balanced relationship with what is
in themselves not holding themselves
back a big piece of this is not holding
yourself back right not getting in your
head not getting angry reactive and
tightening up and then seeking the best
place to be in or inton yourself towards
that best place right like that's it
those are the few peat components if you
have those two components therein lies
hope now reverse that say let's imagine
that's what Paul was saying and see if
that actually ends back on faith so he
says it's the hope of things that are
not yet seen and I guess it's it would
it would MIT it would meet very nicely
especially if you go into the the
Corinthian him towards agape where it
ends where he's proposing the most
excellent way by the way the way of
agape and then he proposes that in the
end we will know as we are known he
proposes a sort of a I suppose it's a
culmination a culmination of
participatory knowing we will know as we
are known right we will we will be in
complete conformity with ultimate
reality and so faith the usual your
metaphor is the hope that sees that as a
path as a way as a way that is
realizable by a committed stance towards
that possibility yeah that would work
yeah that's great and that is great and
there's there's something about that
like okay so let's just check this out
now I'm bringing in that Viktor Frankl
of course it's great established app
let's bring him in bring him in office
up the sidelines no matter where you are
there is always hope which is to say no
matter where you are there is always an
appropriate dispositional stance in
relationship to where you are they're
oriented towards the best possibility of
where you are yes yes that's all we have
to say right which is a possibility in
the sense of a potentiality not just
another biological possibility yeah and
what was interesting about Franco
because if you remember when he was
talking about his time in in the camp he
was very careful to City this goes back
to what we were talking about the sweet
spot he was very careful to situate you
know what he was talking about with
logos by the way logotherapy
idea logos is all connected right was
right he how he differentiated between
the two groups that he saw worked able
to survive in the camps there were the
people who just gave up of course and
they but there was people who actually
had the magical hope they would say no
no and they did willful assertion we
will be liberated on day X I know it I
know it and then they asked would come
and of course the liberation will not
occur and then those people were very
very quickly fall apart they would fall
apart so it's not it's not an assertion
right this hope it's something else it's
I like your idea of turning it into a
verb a verb of orientation and I see it
almost like the kind of reducing of
possibilities that then starts to afford
a very nascent for perhaps constantly
accelerating reciprocal opening yeah
think of it like like child the child
learning how to do something yeah I'll
learn you had a stand or to walk it's
that thing it's like the the the feeling
of the sense the sense of what the the
accomplishment if the developmental
growth is and the the searching of all
the different you know a child learning
how to walk like lurching all over the
place but in that space of possibility
there's a spot over here that is the I
know that is called walking by the way
now we have an integrity in there - yeah
the integration of all the distinct
aspects itself into an increasingly
coherent whole the achieves a competency
yeah and hope is the orientation in that
direction right the correct by the way
it's very important right it's not a
delusional is a correct awareness of in
fact
the presence and the orientation the
directionality and the proximity towards
at that location so that I didn't
usually call that hope I usually I use
the term discernment discernment for
that and a discernment that discloses
and draws out possibilities and starts
to actualize those possibilities
precisely because of the way you have
oriented towards them so is yeah so it
seems to me that right um I I just want
to I just want to emphasize something
here because I know it's not happening
in our discourse but I don't want it to
get lost for people who are listening
we're using a lot of procedural skill
metaphors but I think you and I would
agree that what we're talking about
reaches deeper than procedural knowing
it Reese's into perspectival and
participatory knowing because we're
talking about we're talking about
something even more comprehensive than
the child learning to walk we're talking
about somebody moving from you know
foolishness to wisdom from moving from
wretchedness to blessedness right and
these are more than any more than that
someone but but all one all of us hope
that that's what we're really talking
about yeah yeah yeah exactly exactly and
maybe by the way sooner than we'd like
yeah the more shit hits the fan the more
relevant relevance becomes yes which is
very well said you should put that on a
t-shirt Jordan by the way I was actually
just having a conversation with someone
who has been asked by Facebook what is
the best possible thing they can do in
the contemporary situation and by the
way I want to I want to connect you to
them because the answer is to orient
their efforts towards relevance
realization yes enemy from salience
Landscaping yeah yeah yeah yeah which
which is it you know now easily said
easily enough said and of course not
necessarily easy
done but I imagine that you and
Christopher have might have some very
nice advice on how they might go about
doing that I think we're having the
beginnings of it I think that the I
think that what we're doing here I mean
this is growing in my argument and in my
mind and I think also with Chris that
what you and I are enacting here is a
central piece of how we get to that
cultivation of improved relevance
realization so that salience is tracking
the richness that we've been talking
about I think this is any removable
piece and a central piece to the puzzle
of the practicality that we're
addressing right now I used to think
that purely individual practices you
know meditation contemplation Tai Chi
Chuan I think those are also irremovable
pieces I don't not trying to dismiss
them but I want a foreground now how
important this practice is for refining
and beautifying if you'll allow me that
verb our capacity for relevance
realization that's needed in these kinds
of times and that's part of also what
the religion of the future would be
doing people learning how to commune not
just communicate commune together to
bring about the beautification of their
sensibilities so they can get their
salience landscaping to be tracking the
richness in a reliable way
yes yes absolutely and in fact I've
never minded the conversation I had with
my friend Brett Weinstein have you ever
met Brett no I'd like to at some point
he sees a beautiful beautiful being and
yeah try this this is very nice
and it came to me as he was talking
about our conversations I'm particular
the conversation at the four of us so
you remember Franklin Roosevelt's
fireside chats yeah of course and you're
familiar with the phrase the next Buddha
is a saint huh
I imagine yeah yes okay so Brett has
proposed campfires campfires not
fireside chats because campfires are the
locus of human consciousness it's where
we could become a conscious together yes
so Brett's campfire looks like looks
like our forward dialogue okay but in
the context of of where we are like so
imagine a circumstance where you've
gathered together for people who engaged
in a conversation a dialogue over over
the over the meta-crisis right yep
where where are we and how might we
respond to it never a period of an hour
so they they explore that in dialogue
thoughtful ER carefully
there's no equivocation there are as far
as I can tell
don't bother and they'd be running out
of time I am we appended on this I
apologize that's okay
for very strong values and I will
imagine that you will actually identify
several more from this kind of a process
so one piece is that is the
transformation of the individuals
themselves the actual out the dialogue
they had dialectical process for the
people in the in the dialogue yes yeah
then there is the the content of the
dialogue that which is actually produced
there for other people who are listening
much like as you and I talk there are
things that we say that ours may be
meaningful in and of themselves but then
of course there is the the participation
the engagement in the dialogue meaning
the dialogue oohs of the participants
were over the people who are purchased
or watching the video yeah you know just
sensing and feeling in themselves and in
their own bodies coming into
relationship with dialogue becoming
capable of dialogue in themselves and
beginning to reconnect with that vital
fabric that is a total history of human
consciousness from the first campfires
being part of that entire arc in full
seriousness and responsibility and
empowerment then the fourth is them
doing it themselves yes and people all
over the country people all over the
world choosing to gather around
campfires and engaging in dialogue in
relationship to a crisis a real a moment
where this capacity to do this is the
answer to the question yeah that's
beautiful yeah I'm a deep agreement with
this it's something I've been actively
trying to facilitate and afford and
exemplify I think I think that yeah I
think this is exactly right so I don't
want to keep you because your time is
running out I suggest that we could pick
on this idea of a Brett's idea and and
maybe develop it in our next
conversation together this is wonderful
maybe in fact with Brett that might be
fun
that would be fun I would enjoy that I
would enjoy that all right yeah let's
just think about guys in stock thank you
again it's really nice to see you again
I'm glad that you're healthy and doing
well I feel the same for you and it's
really wonderful to see your little
girls so full of life that's really
wonderful that was a that was a that was
it was a jewel of a moment so thank you
for that yeah you're welcome
about okay take care two weeks from now
we can make time okay so let me know I
will I may make a proposal to you please
okay